Hello and welcome to another code walkthrough
for computer architecture for everybody. In this
walkthrough, we're going to walk through the
uppercase converter. So what this is is this
is again WASM in the JavaScript environment. So
it's output is console.log and that's about it.
It we're not even taking some input. We're going
to hardcode our input. And then what we're going
to do is write a function called make an uppercase
copy of the string. Okay. And so this gives us a
little bit more time to take a bit more look
at WASM. Not that I want you to understand or
code WASM. You may even use AI to help solve
this one assignment. So you're going to take
this uppercase code and you're going to write
a lowercase version of it. So you got to kind
of dig through this code and figure out where
it's doing the uppercase and then switch it to
doing lowercase. And it might be a little bit
of work and you might even use AI a little bit
to help you do this. But I'm just going to walk
through this code to help you out. So we're going
to our output's going to go to console.log. We're
going to create some memory. We're going to put a
string in there at location zero. And then we're
going to make it so JavaScript can execute it.
And so we are going to then say copy and go to
uppercase and we're taking some input variables
some making some local variables. So this
parenthesy funk it basically WASM is a stack
oriented language. So when you go into a funks
you can think of a new stack frame being created
just like you would in any other programming
language. And then so in that stack frame there
are variables that belong in that stack frame
and that's what we're talking about here. And
we're setting some values and getting things done.
and then we have some two instructions or two
instructions that might look a little weird to
you. One is the block. And so the idea there are
no labels in WASM there are constructs. There is
a execution stack. And so when you start a block
and we'll go down to the bottom of this block.
Where's the end of the block? I think the end
of the block is right here. Oh, wait. Oh, I missed
it. Missed it. Come back. Come back. Okay. I think
the end of the block is here. , yeah. No, the
end of the block is here and this is the end of
the loop. And so what happens here is the block
creates a temporary label that only exists in
this block. And you can branch to the loop end.
It doesn't have to be named copy loop end. They
just named it copy loop end because that's what's
going on. So if this branch if true this is a this
is a comparing doing a comparison between
the character to see if it was a zero bite right
and if it we hit the zero bite we're going to
exit the loop and we're going to branch to this
copy end. Now copy end is not the top of this it
is the next statement after the end of the block.
So when you say branch if copy loop end you're
exiting. So, so branches in WA WASM are more about
exiting where you're at and going to the next
place. So, that branch goes to here. There is
no label here. So, if we're doing this in assembly
language, we would put a label here and we would
jump to the label. You're only allowed to jump
out of things or to the top of things. And so,
that's the that's the way we exit it. So, this
is a loop that's reading the data and checking
for a zero bite. And if we get a zero bite, we're
done with the loop. So that is the block. Okay,
block is something that can be exited. Think of
it from a C perspective and a Python perspective
as this is like a break. It's a break out of this
block. BRF dollar copy loop end. Breaks out of the
block that has the the label dollar copy loop
end. So that is just a way to start a block
and get out of the block. So that's like a break
statement. All of the looping in WASM is basically
like a wild true loop both in Python and
in C. It's like an infinite loop. And all we're
doing with this loop statement, it has no logic
to it. It is defining another lo another label.
This label is only accessible between the
beginning and the end of the loop. So here is the
end of the loop and we have we're jumping to the
top. If you don't have this br dollar copy loop,
it's not going to go back up. So the while loop
is not automatic. You have to do something at
the bottom of the loop to go up. This is like a
continue in either Python or C. So continue the
loop. go up to the top. Now there is no automatic
incrementing. There is no plus+ in here. No auto
in range sub five. Nothing. You have got to add
one to your Yeah. So we're going to add one to our
counter. They they're adding one to the counter
with this little four statement bit of code. Four
instruction piece of code. So they're doing the
plus+ as it were or advancing the iterator. It
you have to do it in WAT and you're you're seeing
quickly like whoa this is a pain. Why isn't there
just an increment instruction? There isn't.
There's an add one. You put the current value
of I on the stack. You put the one on the stack.
You add the top two items of the stack and then
you set it back into the I variable and then
you go up to the top of the loop. So this is
like an infinite loop and it goes until at the
top of course it reads the offset piece the
it takes the it takes it doesn't have an offset
lookup 6502 had an offset lookup in it and it says
give me the variable and add the i to it. That's
why you have zerobased arrays. Add it and then
load that. And I don't know what this T does, but
then we're going to check to see if the character
we just got is a zero. And then we're going to
branch out of the loop. Some and then
there are things like like this dollar char. This
is a local variable. And then when we finally get
done with this function, we are going to return
at the end of the function. And then that's going
to clear all that local stuff off the
stack, the stack frame, and then we're going to
go. So if we got our main function, and this
main function is what is going to be called
from the JavaScript. So we're going to grab
the string, we're going to grab its length,
and we're going to call the copy and uppercase
routine, push some things in, and call copy and
uppercase. And then we're going to print out the
output of our function and the length. and then
we're going to be done. Okay, so this is Oh, I
need to talk about if. I didn't talk about if. Oh,
here we go. This is the if. So, this if looks
okay. It's got an if then else. By the way,
there is no LF. You just have to keep nesting your
else's. Else, else. It's like going back 20 years,
30 years. Okay. if and then this it's checking to
see if it's greater. This is really this is a
logic statement. We're grabbing the character.
We're checking to see if it's greater than a
lowercase a or is it le greater than lowercase
a and less than lowerase z less than or equal
to. So it's doing a greater than or equal to and a
less than or equal to. And this and is taking the
two logic results that are sitting on the stack
and then being true or false based on those two
logical results popping it off. So it's a stack
oriented computation. And so if this resulted in
a true meaning it's greater than or equal to a and
less than or equal to z. If it's true we're going
to convert that character by subtracting 32 and
then we're going to store it back in. And so that
is what we're going to do. We're well, we're
going to calculate the character, then we're
going to store it here. It's just really wordy.
I mean, assembly language seems easier. Now,
the reality is most browsers don't execute this
literally. It can, and it's still pretty fast.
You can execute this with an interpreter and
it runs plenty fine, but you can also what's do
what's called cross-co compiling it into native
code. The the key is that the WAT the way it's
written a compiler can verify that this is not
like doing naughty things. It's not like reading
memory doesn't belong to it. You can't jump
to places that don't belong to you. You can't
execute code. There's so many things that stops
you from doing which is that sandboxing thing. So,
so we have gone through our loop. We've converted
all the stuff to uppercase. Left the letters that
are not that are already uppercase alone. And
then we print it all out. So with all that let's
compile it and run it. So remember in this screen
the WAT is being assembled inside the JavaScript.
This is just a JavaScript button. The WAT is being
assembled inside the JavaScript and then it is
being executed inside the browser and the results
are coming back to JavaScript and that's it. So,
we got our uppercase. And your assignment is to
adapt this and adapt it so it does lowercase. It
even tells you like, oh, it's a slightly different
number. Maybe you want to do a different if. There
you go. So, it's not it's not trying to make it
super hard for you, but you got to dig through
here, look enough, and you'll you'll mess it up.
And then you just go reload the sample code. And
then you fix it again until when you run it, it
says the correct output happens. Right? So that
this could all be lowercase and then you will have
passed the autograder. Let's go ahead and run the
autograder on this. It's going to fail. It was You
got to keep the original string. It compiled it.
No, it didn't. We got the wrong one. That's
cuz I didn't change the code. So there you
go. That's your job. You're going to you're going
to fix that in the autograder. Okay. So this is
a little more detail in the walkthrough where
we build a function. We talk about the block.
We talk about how break works, how continue
works and then how if then there is an else
but there is no else if and we talked about
the stack and stack approach. So it's not you
can talk a bunch to AI about this and learn
as much or as little as you want about WASM.
I just wanted to expose you to WASM because
it is going to be increasingly important
going forward when we talk about different
kinds of software de software systems. Cheers.